this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software hello everyone i'm celina for
software engineering radio and I'm here
today with Sam Aaron 702 PhD on
domain-specific languages and now works
as a postdoctoral research associate at
a computer lab at the University of
Cambridge while doing that he has
designed a language a programming
language called sonic PI and that's what
we're going to talk about today so Sam
what is sonic part alright so sonic PI's
I hear new language is more like a
domain-specific language based on top of
the Ruby programming language and it's
essentially turns Ruby into a musical
instruments that anybody can learn and
anyone can experience the creative power
of code so why did he create sonic pi
what is the problem that it solved so
this came back a few years ago when the
Raspberry Pi first came out and it was
incredibly successful as we've all see
now but it surprised everybody at the
time and although they were selling lots
and lots of raspberry PI's the promise
of the raspberry pi was it was going to
have an impact in terms of how we engage
children in learning to program and part
of that problem is making sure that they
have affordable hardware at home which
the raspberry PI's solved but the other
part is making sure there was
interesting software to run on it that
they could use to engage themselves with
and so from the early days scratch was
on there but there was an open question
- what other piece of software could we
potentially build that may potentially
help children engage with programming
and the Broadcom foundation which is a
company which designs the chips they had
a small pocket of money for three month
guerilla projects to see if we could
have a look at this problem and the
questions were banded around
Buddha labs does I don't know anyone who
potentially could work on this and
because I'd already been working on
music software for a number of years
building something called overtone which
is a closure front-end to supercollider
seem like a natural thing to give me a
shot at building something very simple
that was essentially an overtone a live
coding platform but rather lamed at a
professional programmers it was aimed at
children to see if we can lower the
barrier to entry
maybe not all listeners are familiar
with what overtone yes give me you can
you explain that yeah I mean probably to
understand that you also you to
understand what live coding music is and
I'm sure we can talk about that at
length later but the idea really is in
terms of these musical systems that use
code as their interface so instead of
hitting sticks on drums or clinking
strings in your fingers we write codes
we evaluate that code with some system
and the result the side effect of that
evaluation is some music which is
produced or some modification of the
music which is currently playing and so
through the definition and redefinition
of code were able to create musical
compositions and performances overtone
allows this using the supercollider
synthesizer which is a really powerful
open-source synthesizer but as the
interface we use the cloture programming
language which is a list which runs of
the JVM which it's one of my favorite
programming languages it's a really
beautiful language and so it was
interesting to me to explore how a lisp
like language running on the JVM with
always access to libraries which had a
really emphasis on concurrency could be
an interesting platform for exploring
music performance of compositions so
that was overtone which was a project
created originally by chat called Jeff
Rose a close friend of mine but a month
or did he sort of that project I
discovered his existence he discovered
mine and we worked together very closely
since then but despite closure being
your favorite programming language sonic
pie is built on Ruby yes why
mainly because the context with which
the sonic pie language or environment
was created dictated essentially that
closure wasn't wasn't really good fit
there were two main reasons for this one
was that so if I had to burn the
raspberry pie and so
the time the support for jvn was very
weak and starting a closure repple took
minutes not seconds sodding overtone
inside the ratified took about seven
minutes disease probably mostly because
my inefficient programming at a time but
it that wasn't really something that was
feasible but also the environment has to
pass what I would call the head ped
teacher test so the head teachers were
often come to being in workshops I'll be
delivering when they were interested and
asked why are you not using Python and
so I would need to have a very good
reason why I wasn't using Python because
Python is the language in the UK that
pretty much all schools are focused on
so it's scratch to Python and so Ruby
allowed me to answer that question very
simply Ruby is very very very similar to
Python the UK government uses Ruby
Flores open source projects Twitter was
originally built in Ruby although it's
not anymore it's it's still a lead
argument aren't really necessarily
what's correct mods not credits what
passes their head teacher test because
the head teacher doesn't really tend to
know that much about software but wants
to be convinced yeah that's a good
reason so Ruby allowed me to do that
very effectively enclosure it wouldn't
be much more of a struggle to have a
little shopping file feel ashame but it
is the way it is sure so how did you
know how to make the language are you a
musician yourself do you play any
instruments so that's a good question so
some fault that I did a little bit of
music music at school I played Karen and
saxophone and a jazz band no but and
nothing more than that certainly nothing
university nothing later my life's in a
professional music knowledge but it's
just the same as saying to any software
developer if they enter a new business
domain you don't know about the
pharmaceutical industry so how can you
program in that industry if you don't
have any background of course you don't
need a background in industry you need
to be able to have a background of
programming and you go learn about the
programmable aspects of the industry
working in and then you go and work in a
bank or then you go to work in a sports
company then you go and work in a an
environmental company and you can still
take the skills and transfer them and
you learn the aspects of the domain on
the job music is no different and so I
learned about the aspects I'm still very
much learning about
the structural aspects of music on the
job and as I learned that I turn that
knowledge into workable abstractions
within sonic PI that allows me then to
share that knowledge with a broader
audience but if you work in a bank you
have customer that can introduce you to
domain yes who did you have to help you
so at the time when I started working on
domain of music I was working on
overtone and I was I had it was a year
and Amsterdam was two years and I was
working on it then here in Cambridge and
when I really started to apply my
knowledge to learn music with it with
fervor was here in Cambridge and I met a
number of people who had large amounts
of musical knowledge and I brought over
to my house where weekend's bought lots
of beers and it was important then to
try getting on knowledge from their head
into my head and so then I would then
program my I asked them essentially what
is the scale and then they were telling
me and I said well I don't know what
that means and then don't ask them to
give me more more detail until I could
then codify what they said and then
present in the back what they said in
terms of code and once we reach an
agreement then and I knew I'd understood
what they were talking about so it's
really the same as you program for any
industry it's really about trying to
learn and understand the fool that's the
formal aspects of the domain the program
of aspects and then try and represent
that in code yeah so you really use code
there as a means of learning about the
domain by implementing it and slicing
understanding in precisely so one of the
goals of sonic Phi is to be fun for a
very broad audience that your design
goal can you talk a bit more about that
yeah I mean like the the the the most
important design goal which probably
doesn't sound very ambitious but it's
really important is to be able to give
people and that's not just children it's
everybody an initial experience of
programming that doesn't scare them off
and I think that a lot of initial
experiences are really quite terrifying
or I don't have any direct meaning to
people's lives and are very off-putting
in the long term I think that's quite
damaging for a lot of people so for me
trying to figure out how to make that
initial experience friendly and not
scariest was pretty much the only main
goal
and then beyond that of course the
things you're describing become really
important about being fun engaging and
exciting and I think they're all made
for me means of motivating and
engagement and so the question to me
isn't about what aspects of programming
should we teach to me the important
question is how do we find figure out
ways to engage people in programming
that creates meaning in their lives that
the solution is some programming and so
they're learning to do lists because
that the idea the list is has value to
them by now for what they want to
achieve
so a good example of that is we didn't
teach lists we talked bass riffs and so
a bass riff itself is a list of notes
and to perform a bass riff you need to
teach iteration I want to map a function
over that list or I want to for I equals
0 beginning list today there's different
ways of achieving that essentially you
want so in process to work over a list
so that's to make a bass line it's not
to sort a list of numbers or just print
out a list of numbers on the screen
because I don't think that's necessarily
engaging to a broader audience yeah so
you take a problem or a task that
someone already wants to do like making
a song yep try and express that with
source code you show them that they can
do things that they couldn't do before
with code so it gives them new powers
however what's really different from
other programming languages for children
like scratch for example scratch isn't
all that fun if you're a grown-up well
after a while you know it's a toy and
you get you yeah it's still oozing it
appeal but solid pie is also used by
adults especially live performance that
from life coding we will talk more about
that later in the interview so why is it
important to have language that has such
a broad audience I mean you could make
one language for kids and one language
for performance or special versions of
the language or different versions of
the IDE why do you want a
one-size-fits-all solution um this Bobi
two main reasons for that I can think of
right now
first of all there's just one me
building to think and so if there was
100 of me there maybe we could explore
multiple things you just described
multiple vote
multiple iterations so the constraint
our development time is an important
thing to consider but but also it's
really important to me that text or the
idea me in my head I see sonic pie like
a piano all I combine in where or like a
guitar these instruments have evolved
over many hundreds of years it's not
really a fair comparison but they can
talk about the where these things can go
in a few hundred years when what what
would be the equivalent of sonic part a
few hundred years model it look like I I
hope it would have the similar
properties of guitar which is anybody
can walk up to a guitar pick it up and
make some sounds anybody can learn how
to play all of the notes on the guitar
in five minutes because you just need to
hold your finger on a fret and pluck a
notes and you move your finger up and
down the fretboard and you get different
notes and you can move across the
strings and you get different notes so
you can learn it in the same as a piano
you can learn how to play all the notes
of the piano and in very short amount of
time but to master piano that's a really
difficult thing but why would you master
piano that's because there are pianists
who have spent many years who can do
amazing things and so it's one thing to
make something simple and easy to work
with like the piano is but to me there's
no real value in that unless there's
deep motivation to aspire to something
that other people are able to do and so
having the simple approach it's just the
starting point having the the
motivational valuing seeing what you
could do if you spend in many years
practicing and working on this I think
that's why people pick up a guitar it's
not because it's simple to pick up it's
because they've seen their favorite
guitarists do amazing things on stage
and so to me sonic PI one of the goals
is to see if that kind of a view of the
world could be applied to software could
it be possible that people would pick up
software not because they've been told
to in school but because as people they
respect in the world musicians maybe
that are using similar software that
they could then think well I want to do
that too that that makes total sense
that this sort of showmanship of life
performing also has the role of getting
children in but maybe also other people
that aren't necessarily programmers by
job but they think that looks nice I
wouldn't be like that person so that
that high-level goal of making it simple
but also powerful how does that
translate into concrete goals for the
language what decisions you made in the
syntax of the language or the features
that help you achieve that goal
yeah they are very hard constraints to
meet
so with overtone my previous system that
was with my Jeff we just used to think
of cool ideas and then we used to think
could we build those ideas and if we
could we built them and so the system
expanded quite rapidly in is very
powerful set of features and if people
are interested in learning closure and
already are professional programmers
then it's a really great environment to
start with but sonic PI trying to reach
a broader audience load is trying to
lower the value to entry and so if your
barrier to entry is you need to have a
compliant ID like Emacs you know or
IntelliJ and you need to understand the
folks for programming there's a lot of
these barriers and so it's not just good
enough to think about it is a cool idea
it then has to pass through the test of
could I improve on the idea which then
has to pass the test of if I do
implement this idea does it test like
well with other ideas does it fit in and
in terms of a cohesive design which I
think most programmers would already
understand and probably if you figure
out if you're designing an API you would
make if you're gonna add a new endpoint
you think well how does this fit in
where will the other endpoints but
there's another layer which is really
really fundamental which then is if I
can have an idea which passes all these
tests so I've got the idea I can
implement it
it's fit so well with the rest of the
design then I have to ask the question
could I imagine teaching this design
this idea to a 10 year old child and
nine times out of ten the answer is no
and so then I stop and so and we repeat
miss rate so I have many ideas which are
floating around in space right now my
head which I'd like to build but I
haven't yet figured out how to make it
simple enough for a 10 year old child so
can you give an idea of something you
would want to include but go delete it
because you thought there's there's just
no way I can explain
this to a child yeah so an idea at the
moment which I really want to have which
is the musical idea which is called
side-chaining so if I take my didn't
that so so this is a Sunnah technique
used in dance music where few half
example the kick drum bang what tends to
happen is when the kick drum kicks in
the rest of music is the volume is
reduced just the duration of kick drum
and then brought back up again so what
that does is it gives space in the music
in the mix for the kitchen to happen and
something called a compressor is used
for this it's all very technical but I
really like it's a really nice sound
really sound that children been used to
hearing and so it'll be great to be out
of a very simple way of just having that
effect but the current way that sonic PI
implements effects is using closures and
there's a very clear nesting of closures
I can have a closure inside of a closure
and sort of a closure so I can
essentially chain effects very easily by
having effect inside of an effect side
an effect like an onion ring but the
idea of sidechain requires you to have
to civil tendency and there's I haven't
gotten a simple way of creating a syntax
yet that's going to allow them to do
that so I could easily build it but I
couldn't imagine teaching a ten-year-old
child how to do essentially create a
lambda function and passing it as an
argument to another but it's already too
much yeah so how do you obtain knowledge
about what ten-year-old kids understand
because you say I cannot imagine how to
do it have you had features that you've
tested with children and that you remove
later because it just didn't work with
that actually no so what happened was
that the first version of site pi took
me two weeks to build because we had a
three months period to do the whole
project and then after those two weeks I
was in classrooms observing children
using the system and so from day one
really it was built within classrooms
with teachers with observation children
and so all of the features grew
initially for the first year and a half
through direct observation with children
on a multitude of different projects all
over the UK and so I really can say with
assertion that during that period that's
every feature I built the kids could use
because I'm very careful to slowly build
the features and what
their observation since then there's
been a focus on music aspects as much as
the computer science teaching aspects
but I've used my knowledge of my
observations of the children and then
also use my relationships with teachers
for discussions to figure out if I did
this do you think that will be okay and
so there's a lot of discussion or a
discourse a lot of reflection that goes
into this process on are features that
you regret that's a good question
I yes and I removed them and so I have
no problem with backwards-compatible
which one then why so let me think about
this so so for example I initially
implemented the randomization system
using so ruby has ran function like
every other phone every program language
and I used that to great effect to allow
people to be able to say to two random
notes from the pentatonic scale and that
was a great way of easily making
compositions without having to compose
because you can just say choose me a
bunch of notes if I don't like them
choose another bunch of notes until I do
like them and that was great but what it
didn't really allow most things like
being able to reproduce my performances
across runs of the software or if I set
my code or somebody else I want them to
hear the same piece of music because it
would do the randomization again you
would get a different brand differently
very time yeah and there's also things I
want figured out what I want to do if I
had a line of code in an iteration that
called a random value and that produced
me my baseline and then I say I wanted
to randomize another aspect of the music
saying it's Sombra if I then call that R
and then I'm calling it twice which then
interferes with the first set of RAD so
now get different baseline so I wanted
to be able to be able to undo calls
Durant which is like taking a card from
the deck and then putting it back on
again so when I take the next card it's
the same one and so typical programming
languages don't really support undoing
the side effect of calling a random
value of a random function and so I then
had to then go back Andreea moment sonic
pines randomization system using a much
simpler of less random approach they
were but random enough to allow me to
have these
features which has now but what that
meant is that early compositions which
huge randomization now no longer work
because the randomization sisters how
did you solve that
well you can't yeah mainly because
because by new randomization system
isn't infinitely random you actually try
to do a depth search of trying to find
that composition in there and the new
random system that couldn't find it so I
had to change the competition
so you just communicating users sorry
people we've changed something and your
your Stewart song might change sound
very different in this new version yes
exactly and every version of the solid
part hasn't for release less time as a
felicitous of changes that are
incompatible and I mean I attempt this
is a this was a big change there aren't
that many of them which it was broad
impact impacting as this but at the time
the world not many people I could
observe using this speak to anyway so I
don't think there was a radical
certainly wasn't any lashed back and the
community there's no one really you
mentioned it so I think so that other
thing that was that much impact
obviously as the software grows my
ability to make this change is going to
diminish but I'm still in favor of
breaking backwards compatibility where
it makes sense in terms of making it
simpler for new users who are going to
join the community so talking about the
pub usual bridge because you're already
internet it a little bit you say well I
didn't see people use this feature
anyway how big is the user base and how
do you know what people are using it so
I have a few ways of observing obviously
you can never know this I know that
sonic PI calls home to ask for there's
an update so I can see how many people
are asking for updates so these are
people using sonic PI that haven't opted
out from that feature you can turn them
off if you want to remain anonymous and
they're about three and out three
hundred thousand users who've done that
then there's also the Twitter feed which
i iost my searchable people mentioning
sonic PI and Twitter and so there's
everyday there's a number of people who
tweet about it so I get to see the
community that way and there's also the
main list as well where people
discussing ideas so these are the three
main points I can observe the community
centers and you have any idea what the
biggest part of the community is is it
children playing at home is it in school
settings or professional musicians i I
think that
the largest set of people I've observed
our workshops and lessons in schools but
actually less um lessons more on
workshops so people giving impact
workshops or introductory workshops or
exploratory workshops and programming
that I've seen lots of activity all
around the world of that kind I see some
activity which is growing in schools but
that's a really tough problem which we
can discuss if you want to
there were many barriers to that already
that we have to find ways through and in
terms of the professional people that
were I've seen I don't think there were
that any professional life coders using
sonic private moments or and
professional musicians yet but there are
larger and growing number of people who
are using it do have musical outputs and
the kind of music they're making is
increasingly more exciting to me to hear
so yes it when people start playing
sonic pipe just like when people start
playing the piano
it all sounds fairly similar but as
people are creating their own styles
that's really exciting to watch
so does that impact the language if you
here's a piece of music that someone
created do you think it would be even
better if it also had that musical
feature and there's a template impact
the language absolutely
and also when I observe people doing
things which I don't feel like idiomatic
I then haven't then somehow communicated
what did you imagine
yes and so then I think about how do I
try and coerce these people in the
future to follow that do you mean
idiomatic in terms of how to write the
source code or idiomatic in terms of how
to music sounds oh oh absolutely the
source code I don't want to make any
impact at all on what music people would
make because I believe that's their
expression of their own personal ideas
and that's not for me to have any filter
over however there are number of times
where I know that if someone had written
their source website differently they
would have given them more freedom to be
able to move from that because another
way to think about live coding music is
it's a bit like exploring and driving
around a known unknown territory or
walking in an unknown territory and
there are certain places which is like
dead ends and there are certain places
which give you five different directions
you can go in and I know that certain
forms of the code are more like dead
ends and there
like points of of varied movements can
you give a concrete example because it's
all very abstract until you really get
involved in these things it's very hard
to see this but one clear thing is the
manipulation of management of time sight
fighters are very strange things of time
it can play around in new and exciting
ways that allows you to then work with
lots of things which manipulate time at
the same time Oh again I'm still working
away absolutely so let's think of a
concrete example so if we have an effect
so I can make a sound which makes us
noise blow a beautiful sound and then I
can apply an effect to it so I can add
reverb to it or I can distortion to it
and that's for the lexical closure or I
can slice it so that that means that
I've got someone in the volume knob
turning it on or off so instead of going
blur it's blep blep so that's I could do
it quickly but it over there or solely
blur look and so the rate of on half of
the slicer is a temporal has time now if
I also have a beats a sample a
pre-recorded sample that has rhythm and
into it
and I play at rhythm at the same time
I'm playing my slicing of my sound if
the slicing isn't in the same tempo as
the beats that might sound incorrect to
Sonny is it's so simple text sometimes
it's might be exactly what you want but
other cases it might not and so then the
question is well how do I make sure that
actually sound good together and so
there are certain constructs and
tactically you can use which can make
that much easier to make these the same
time that others and of course allow you
to change the whole BPM the whole speed
of the entire track and without having
to change the slices speed having to
change the sample speed you're changing
them both simultaneously well then how
do you gather money link control them
both independently so the syntax allows
users to say something like align these
two piece of things you don't have to
think about it yourself the language
encourages you yes
if you want to have it not lines then it
was harder to do in this in fact exactly
where the Donnie do magic way is to not
have the lines and then suddenly it's
much harder to then gonna live and go to
modify a lot more code or people ask for
why does it sound not very good and so
this is a again to this approaches that
I've solved it so I haven't sold it but
I try and solve it by more clearly in
the documentation explaining where where
you should or shouldn't do this or if
people tweet for example your melody
I'll write them back and saying that's
great but you might want to consider
using this approach and then link to the
documentation so that they're aware
there other ways of doing what they do
so it's very interesting that you do
that on Twitter but this would be
something that would be in your OEE as
well you'd suggest refactoring saying
hey this is not the way you do it is
this something you are thinking about
absolutely there's lots and lots and
lots of thing something you have but
it's just the amount of time and an
effort so there's anyone listening who
would look to get involved in there's
tons and tons of things to work on yeah
and I think making the IDE communicate
more things to the user is clearly only
a good thing so I want to communicate
not just what refactorings are possible
or what we configurations are possible
I don't want it also to be able to
enable live refactorings on an ASD basis
so I wanted to consider moving away from
text recommendation to tomorrow's ast
recommendation in the code like a
scratch does for example allow edits to
do tree transformations that kind of
thing would be really powerful but I
also want the code itself to come alive
as it's executing so the moment you
write some code you press run and then
you hear the music this is a log which
describes the process that's going
through but once you get to a similar
context to that log just flies by like
like you know if you go to if you've got
a popular website and you look at the
Apache logs it's just flying by yeah you
can't really do anything meaningful with
it as a human looking at the locks and
so are the ways to animate the text that
in time to the music allow me to say
well this is the live loop which is
going really fast or this is this go
slowly or this is where this this is the
source of this sound is here yeah
because there are some languages for
broke probably in language for children
like Lego Mindstorms for example
highlights the blocks that are being
executed a sausage it's often beautiful
day vision example does this with his
block language which is a lisp which
uses 3d graphics and it's a beautiful
thing to watch as a performance but it
really does clearly communicates what's
happening in terms of their execution
process talking about go quality there's
of course a apart from refactoring also
testing and normally you have tests for
your source code and if you run it you
and you make it change then the desk
will break I understand that with only
fire you can just listen to the source
code but can you imagine in testing
environment as well if there's something
really funky and your sound changes a
lot it's the only way for the listener
to listen that's a very good question I
I mean obviously I've thought about this
in terms of the development of the
software itself but I never think about
testing as when I'm performing ever not
saying it doesn't have any value just
hasn't ever been something that I've
seen in media but it with mainly because
the liveness of the situation is kind of
a testing environment already people
already talked about repple driven
developments as a as a way of
reproducing much of the perceived
benefits of test-driven development and
you can see some similarities there I'm
not drawing any sides but you can sort
of see it and so when you do live
performing live programming live coding
there the time for you to observe what
happened is so sure that it's very easy
then to go back and forth and do it and
to treat your code like play and not
think of it as a structure that needs to
test it it's just a form that has the
right form in the moments or doesn't if
it doesn't have the right form and you
can just tweak it into the tests so I
can't remember who makes me Tommy this
absolute this analogy but it's a really
important one right now which is if you
imagine the goal to be hitting a target
in a remote distance more approach would
be to get a bow and arrow of the same
kind of quality in the Olympics with all
of the eye sights and the tunings and
the weights and and really and then you
be the more like testing because what
you're doing is you're saying I'm going
to make take into account
we flow and then they've taken cut the
distance and the weight of the arrow I
mean I'm gonna do some mathematical
calculations to make sure that I'm gonna
guarantee to get that far and you can
spend a lot of time setting the bone
arrow up and then firing it hoping is
gonna hit the target or you just get a
hose
Shh start spraying it randomly and then
you need to ask the question am I going
further away or closer to the target
right and then you just keep go closer
closer closer than you hit it and so
live program to me is much more laughs
approaches much more ad hoc but because
you have this lioness you didn't have to
do all this before hands setting up the
structure and testing and and creating
mathematical models to make sure you
you're gonna be accurate because you
have the ability to change it so let's
talk about code as performance art a
little bit more because that's where
we're going anyway
there are even parties for this right
right I understood there something
called an algorithm to people performing
with source code absolutely there's
something called the Alpha rate
movements which was started by Alex
MacLean and Nicholas Collins and Perry
they would go on a car journey into
distance listening to happy hardcore
something there's all this great
turmagar I've come to the head and what
that turn into is this large movement of
individual people creating parties where
the main instrument is code and a lot of
that's live coding
so people modifying the code improvising
life but some of its people preparing
compositions beforehand as well and
going and hitting execute which may
contain machine learning or may contain
randomization systems but predominately
the idea is that you have algorithms
making the music which is - I'll go with
the algarve and the red part is pointing
back towards to the rave movement of of
parties where dance music was was a
really big important thing and mainly
because I think it's actually very easy
typically relatively to make dance music
from cones and is to make other music
because of the repetition is something
that code can do quite clearly with
loops in iteration and it's great to see
a range of people from all sorts of
backgrounds and disciplines
both from the programming backgrounds
academic
musical backgrounds all making music
together for other people to listen to
and to see the range of languages and
tools and uses is a beautiful thing so
often that these parties people aren't
just looking at the performer but the
source code is also on the screen
absolutely yes which is very cool but
it's like saying it to me it's like
imagine going to guitar again to the
guitarist who then hides their guitar
behind a curtain like you question that
so to me projecting the source code is
just like showing people your guitar is
just an obvious thing to do ya know if
you sail again it makes so much sense
but it's still strange they're still
here to a party don't tend to
communicate the audience the process in
which they are making the music life and
I think that live coding projecting the
source code offers the performer an
opportunity to demonstrate the process
they're making that then can include the
audience so that those that impact a
language again because you want to have
a readable syntax so people can
understand what you're doing I think
that if you ask a number of people in
the live coding community people to
perform these things you'll hear a
variety of answers to that question so I
can only be the answer for my
perspective and for me I think it's very
very very very important that the
audience if they want to not all the
audience will want to can perceive some
of what's going on in terms of the code
so there's a number of ways to achieve
that one is to make sure the language is
more easily understood and so one of the
benefits of working in classrooms is
I've made sure that my language instead
of up by 10 year olds but I also turned
out to be making it fairly
understandable to audiences who never
seen the system before but also it's not
just about making the language simple
it's also about making the presentation
simple so one of the things I try and do
is to work with large fonts so the code
is large on the screen so that means I
have to reduce demand of algorithmic
complexity in terms of syntax which
sunscreen obviously allows you to
libraries and leave the scene so I'm
able to to maintain some level of
complexity in terms of the output but in
terms of the interaction of the system
I'm trying to make that as simple and
read
as possible and my observations have
been at when I'd like for example I
performed in a gig in America when I
made the code really simple so who time
I made section to the other performance
so simple to move code it was one or two
lines that I observed in the audience
they just stopped and stared and so when
I made it similar filters to read they
could actually read it and they did read
it and then when I wrote when I
communicated to them through comments so
I can write a comment in the source code
doing it would laugh and engage and
cheer based off what I was saying so
people were actually reading the source
code to lament them to take me to cake
with them so I wouldn't believe that's a
very for me it's a very very important
thing so do you want something in the
language or any I need to very quickly
change because if you're performing and
it sounds bad you have to be very
reactive what specific features that you
have for that so I have let me think of
an example so I have a system called a
live loop which is kind of an inversion
of something called temple recursion
created by Andrew sciences not everyone
could you please explain exactly so I
think the library was actually easy to
explain that's why I created it but I
wants to make sure that the provenance
of it is it's clear to the audience the
ID of the library is that it's just a
loop you say Lu program some code but
the rival OOP has one important
difference it has a name
so I call my live you foo or bar or bass
and the way to think about this is that
it's a performer all right so Sam's
performing and Sally's performing and so
that in my band I can have multiple
members and but they all have to have
unique name so I'm able to say Sam get
the bass going John you do the drums
Sally can you do the cymbals and in that
sense I already have introduced one
strange concept a lot of programmers
there's my loops my live loops have a
notion of code concurrency already so
you can have multiple live loops running
at the same time so they're more like
agents or something or actors in a
context and then in addition the
behavior of the live loop is something
you can modify on the fly to so you can
say I like my library to do this I play
a bass drum bang bang bang
and then after a while say well actually
you know what bass drum can you play a
cymbal
so I change its definition and next time
we're in the live loop it plays the
cymbal and so I'm able then to to modify
what's going on on the fly and to be
able to changes and so in terms of the
features these features are important
but also times while the live loop
manages its own time so that it's it
stays exactly on time depending on how
you describe the delays between drums
hits so if I say oh you to play a drum
wait for half a second play a drum so
sonic pie that would be sampled drum
seat for half a second I have a live
loop lively food do sample drum sleep
half second end and that will play my
drum if I then change the sample to
cymbal the next time around the library
will play the cymbal or if I change a
sleep time to be longer it would slow
down the live loop or speed up do you do
that change within the live loop yes
so if programmers are sitting at home
the implementation with users and I gave
a talk at strangely a couple of years
ago if you look online we can analyze
the absolutely which disc explained all
this in detail but essentially it's just
each live loop is a thread which
executes which calls which has a body
which is an infinite loop which calls a
function you can redefine and so by
redefining the function that implements
the live you'll be able to change its
behavior next time if dereferences that
function and causes and so in terms of
how do I deal with mistakes be made or
one mistake to be make is that so if I
have four live loops going to example
and when I press run they all start at
the same time because I have this lovely
notion of time just inherited by all
threads I can I can go into detail by
this if you want to but just to try and
keep it at this level it's just when I
press run everything starts in time I if
I if I put a mistake in one of the live
loops if I put a typo in there obviously
not get a run time error in this point
that live loop will die but the other
live loops will still be running so if
I'm performing a good tape is to have
multiple live loops so that when you
make a mistake in one and you will make
mistakes only that one live loop suffers
and the master start going and the
certain little silence then you can sort
of pretend I wanted to do then the goal
then is to get to fix the mistake and
then get the library running again
that's easy but also to get it running
again
in time with everything else and so when
you press the Run button to start the
code again it will start that live loop
from when you press the Run button so
you'd have to somehow manually hit Roman
just the right time to get that live up
to started synchronization with others
you can get them to sync up easily so
again this is the way I build a system
called sync which allows me to write
with syntax to say this live a procedure
this other life loop so that it will
work through the Bible to go around
before it starts the next one so with
syntax I can then fix the problem of
having to worry about timing the live
loop together and that's again that was
quite a complicated system to build but
it's actually very simple to use this is
what the poles simple interpreter
interface doesn't always mean simple in
terms of implementation of design that
she doesn't exactly yeah so performance
does indeed influence the syntax or the
things you can precise because also you
need to think about if I'm hearing the
music and it sounds nice
I imagine where the music could go to I
want to try and make sure that the the
amount of syntax changes I have to write
to make that change isn't too great I
don't have to introduce accidental
complexity in terms of describing that
difference I just want to describe
surely that difference as clearly as
possible so if we talk about when we
when you build a design there's some
level of a central complexity that you
have to have that design to even work
well then whatever material you're using
to build that design and some extra bit
of complexity that's just annoying but
you just have to do it yeah you know and
the amount of that extra complexity is
also a function design as well worse
designs will require more accidental
complexity and so trying to reduce our
extent of collection is a really key in
terms of reducing the amount of syntax
you have to write or modify or things
you have to think about when you're
performing and you want to try make sure
you're just thinking about the music and
not thinking about lots of other things
that are just annoying yeah I think from
language design perspective that's
really very interesting because also
often if you design a language or even
an API you say well the user just has to
do this three goals and then they have
ice eggs sorting our entire library have
a drink yeah yeah you can't you can't
train people you know so you another
level would be if I write this function
in this function it the system breaks
for example because it's a book net one
solution in a business context is to
train the users never to do it yes and
that's a perfectly fine affordable
solution if you have the ability to
control use if you're used to
schoolchildren you can't train them to
not do that course they're going to do
that and so you have to make sure the
system is resilient enough to manage and
deal with that yes so you want to make
it as simple as possible for those
things to be to be achievable
so it's interesting because you keep
comparing sonic PI to musical
instruments I guess it's a means of
performance which I totally see however
there's a variety of musical instruments
and they can play together whereas sonic
PI is one language to make all the music
do you envision you would get
specialized versions of sonic PI that
that there would be an evolution in two
different forms absolutely
I just haven't got to the stage of
maturity in the project that allows for
example the equivalent of Java jars or
Ruby gems for people to add extensions
that's something that I'm working on
that will be there at some point to then
allow people tend to modify the way I
see it at the moment is that surprised a
very good base set of semantics which
manages timing emerges effects chains
manages modification of code and does it
in a really robust way and so to me that
there that sort of semantics to build
things on top off and so I can totally
imagine people building their own
abstractions on top of mine which gives
them different affordances and then
sharing these abstractions with others
which then would create new kinds of
instruments or new ways of more
effectively creating certain kinds of
music if that makes any sense
I can imagine functions that people
might write which we would give them
some parameters which would have great
control in certain kinds of contexts of
music making and then people share those
functions with others
then that's that's a great way of
collaborating to create new kinds of
adapted instruments in many ways there's
also the idea of of synchronizing
temporally multiple computers together
that's something that Blanco has been
doing for a long time but again this is
something which is technically feasible
and a bit fiddly but it's not something
I can imagine a ten-year-old child doing
yet so we need to make something that's
a simpler apple just released a new app
for their pond things yes and one of
their goals was you open up the box you
press the button and you've got
listening to music that's and although
there's always complicated protocols
going on behind the scenes from the user
perspective you open a box that you've
just bought you press a button on your
iPhone and you can listen to music
that's the level of suggestive
for it to be something that teachers are
prepared to pick up in the classroom
because loft and teachers don't want to
be doing Network synchronization right
that's nothing they don't have the
training or knowledge to do so these
things need to be in place first before
we were able to do effective
synchronization which then would then
lead to things like sonic PI orchestras
or being able to have something pipe
talking to any of you the fat fabulous
life coding system to exists so how do
musicians feel about this do they see
sonic PI as a new musical instrument or
after being composers that have created
pieces with a normal traditional
instruments and sonic PI how will it
change music that's very good question I
could spend probably the rest of the two
rounds describing this for at least I
had mixed responses so I've had
conversations with eminence musical
educators who have a very traditional
view of music and those conversations
are often being almost friction for even
aggressive you know in a mild manner of
this is not music this is music and
important sort of Western score which is
only one vision of museums much more to
me than just Western notation and dots
and safe but still they would ask the
question and so they would then be I
would say I believe this is actually is
a new notation for music I don't think
to be interesting direction to go and
then they would say is that can you
do this and they will say some fancy
Italian word pianoforte whatever it is
and I'd save them no idea what you've
just said could you explain it to me in
simple terms okay and they would write
this down in simple terms and they say
are okay and then I'll be able to write
the code and they'll be able to do that
and then they would go oh what can I do
and this would this would happen for
about five six iterations and still
there would be unconvinced it was music
so there's that kind of strange
traditionalist view that that's going to
struggle to be changed which is very
entrenched in the music world but then
there are musicians in while using it I
mean there are I have seen operas being
written with sonic PI people talked
about I have seen I've seen I've seen
schoolchildren doing assembly
performances to the rest of the school
that ten-year-old children we've told
themselves how to do this thing who have
been practicing on the internet using
FaceTime so that's that's a fabulous
thing to see of course I've seen the
algorri to talking about people
performing the sonic PI so that it is
entire possible then there's also this
there are music magazines and example
the Rolling Stone they covered a sonic
PI gig and said that it's for them they
saw it as a reemployment future for
music they said either that the performs
even transcended the presence so I think
that now when when traditional magazines
like that are understand and they also
said that the code made the music making
process more transparent and they were
drawing direct coalition to synthesizers
which they said would be much more
confusing and complicated which is I
thought was a very interesting statement
to make so for even a music magazine to
get that code could actually represent a
simpler way of making music a more
approachable way of making music it was
a fabulous results yeah that's very
impressive because if people use a
synthesizer you can't really see what
knob starts running and your knobs are
syntax so precise follow along that's
cool yes and also synthesizers are
expensive they're really expensive to
set up and buy this is your ax thing
which is which are fabulous buy each
module as one hundreds and hundreds of
euros only buy
free right and opens let's mention that
because it's just wonderful it doesn't
pop in his MacBook Pro it runs in a
recipe pie so talking about programming
for children because you started in
there at the Raspberry Pi to make it
very accessible why is it important for
children to learn programming it's a
very good question
and I think that when you hear answers
they're often related directly to
business and the shortage of programs in
the world and although I have some
appreciation of that as a problem I
still I don't think that the lack of of
workforce should really be the thing
which directs what people are educated
it to be honest I think that is there a
lack of footballers in the world should
we should we emphasize sports teaching I
mean are we teaching mathematics to
create more professional mathematicians
are we create a teaching English to
create more people who write or read
other thing that's the case so although
I think that that I sympathize with the
lack of programmers and I think it'd be
great to have more programmers I don't
think that should be the reason people
learn to program to me what I think is
important is to see that the world we
live in is ever increasingly affected by
programming the programming is affecting
all industries as affecting all our
creative pursuits and that's not a bad
thing it's a fabulous saying that if we
learn how to program it gives us more
power as humans to express ourselves in
new ways and to me that's the main
motivation to learn to program just like
we learn to read a right not to be a
professional reader or to be a
professional writer need to read a right
because it allows us to communicate our
thoughts and ideas both personally and
professionally
I believe that programming has similar
role to play in society so what are the
forms of expression
do you imagine children could do its
first code apart from obviously music we
talked about how to lull in this podcast
so this is this is an important thing to
talk about because when we talk about
programming the often we talk about it
directly for industry I wonder how many
of these podcasts people listen to happy
industry focused I mean and how much of
the programming world in the future is
going to be purely industry focused I
think we already live in a very skewed
world and I think that it's not just
interesting to talk about what
expressive forms code could allow today
it's also important to think about what
it could like tomorrow and where could
it take us and so already today there
are many pursuits you could take like
like music like art there's processing
for exemple let's do beautiful pictures
there's lots of ways to use programming
to build things that allow you to some
robots or things that can fly or they
use a flashing torque or you can imagine
something like a magician and you can
use programming if if it's useful to
make that thing a reality so there's
many many many many ways we can use
programming to help us to communicate
and build our ideas and to share them
and to express ourselves and I really
think we should as a society in general
but also as a community of programmers
we should be celebrating all of the non
industry procedure we could take the
programming and placing a huge a
priority on that because it's a non
industry pursuit which you can have the
largest change in the world I think then
the industry wants that's an interesting
and a very good thought and I'm really
curious to see what what all the
children that you've been teaching and
other people have been teaching who come
up with forms of self-expression with
code so we're really getting right now
and you gave one of the countries that
has achieved the most in this because in
the UK programming at schools it has
been mandatory for two school years yes
so what is your take on that is is this
artists succeeding is it a good thing
how is it going I think it's a fabulous
thing that the the peer group that was
created competing at school headed by
sound Putin Germans and others was
listened to by the governments and was
turned into a curriculum that's a
fabulous thing and now we are able to
have a conversation which is along the
lines of teaching people office skills
like PowerPoint and spreadsheets isn't
just the most important thing about
programming it's also important to be
able to build the next power points and
the next spreadsheet and that
conversation is a real conversation that
people having which is fabulous it's not
to say that learning how to use a
computer as an office tool isn't
important and it should remain to be
important but there's a another deeper
set of skills that really should be
understood to some level by
people and so that this is a for me this
is a really important thing
but the problem is though that although
the government of time politics now had
changed that in the curriculum it
provided and still to this day hasn't
provided any financial support for any
change to happen so there's no money to
be paying for teachers to retrain
because a lot of teachers are really
struggling because the teachers were
teaching and do office or how to design
a nice logo as part of the IT class and
now how to teach algorithms and that's a
large job to make for a lot of teachers
and some of those teachers are very
happy to self learn which is fabulous
but others are going to really struggle
and they really need support and help
and so it's fabulous that charities like
the Raspberry Pi foundation offer free
training they have something called Pike
Adam II which teachers can sign up to
which is a two day course which sort of
bump starts them into having again not
to teach them everything but to make
them not scared of programming is really
the main goal and to give them access to
a community and to allow them to see
that programming isn't actually that
hard it's just a bit frustrating and
different and that a large part of the
thing is that you don't need to have all
the answers you just need to be able to
know who to ask the questions to which I
think every professional knows this
every professional knows that you can't
know all libraries but you know how to
learn the libraries that you need to do
your work
yeah because teachers are used to having
all the answers they know everything in
elementary school about language about
mathematics and every question a kid can
have they can answer but that's
something you have to work go into you
know and I think that's something that's
changing in education in general like
the source of knowledge is the internet
they're not the teacher the teacher
really should be in my opinion more a
facilitator of learning or than the
deliverer of knowledge our part of being
a facilitator is recognizing that there
will be individuals in the class who
know more than you or it's also
accepting that you don't know the answer
something but you can go and find it out
and next week can come back with the
answer and that's not a problem it
shouldn't be a perceived as being a
problem saying I don't know something
isn't a sign of weakness Society means
assignment strength to be a a real sign
of weakness is saying I don't want to
know that thing that's
no problem oh I don't get that and I
never will get that that's that should
be the thing which is attacked and
challenged what we should be encouraged
is I don't know that but I'm gonna learn
am really excited to know what that
might be learning is hard for everyone
otherwise the SyFy have specific
resources for teachers if there are
people listening that are a teacher or
no a teacher does we are our main
resource is the moment for sonic PI
there's the tutorial which is built into
the application itself which has been
translated into multiple languages which
is the best way to get started it's
written assumes you know nothing about
music or anything about code either so
if you know a little bit about either
you'll be able to fly through it
and if you don't you'll be able to work
through it at a good pace and my promise
to the listeners at home is if you're
reading through the tutorial and
something doesn't make sense that's my
problem not yours and if you can let me
know where there's some difficulties
then I will fix them for next people so
there's a tutorial there's also a book
which is freely available as well which
has lots of ideas in terms of so it was
written as a series of chapters for the
magpie magazine for the Raspberry Pi and
so that's another sort of resource as
well but then for teachers the Raspberry
Pi website has a specific computer
science curriculum for introductory
computing that we've written myself and
kerri-anne Philbin who is a tea-tray I
collaborated with and that's freely
available open a Creative Commons
license
and that's on the Raspberry Pi website
the fact I think they have two sources
submitted that we will make sure will
link to all yeah thanks you promise and
then there's there's a project which I
worked on which was Nesta funded a
digital R&D for the Arts St which was
focusing on computers not computer
science but music lessons and so we have
a start solve a music curriculum for
schools available for people to read as
well that's on sonic PI live encoding
calm awesome well I think we covered
most of what sonic Phi is it's a
language for sort for performing with
source code that's inclusive of young
children is there anything you want to
add then I forgot I could talk for hours
but I don't have hours I'd like to say
thank you to everyone supported me for
the work I'm doing and that it's
important that I meant
that's all though we talked at great
length about sonic PI and live coding to
certified one of many live coding
systems and there's a whole range of
different systems that people can play
with and if people are already
programmers and they already have their
favorite language then you'll likely
find a live coding system in your
language that you can play with for
example if you're a Haskell programmer
there's title if you're a Ruby
programmer there's other things than
sonic pie that people have written
people oohing their own direct comment
no overhead maybe Phantom links which
actually do the synthesis in Ruby itself
there's lower environments that's
JavaScript environments as Python
environments so go and find an
environment for your language but if
you're interested in a recent way to get
started that tries it's best to make
sure everything every aspect of the
design is similar for a ten year old
child and there's not other many other
languages that try and do that so Pius
will fit those goals hopefully and if it
doesn't let me know and I'll fix it
Thanks so there's just no excuse for any
programmer out there to become a
musician with a range of live
programming tools out there precisely
and and and what I would like people to
do if they're professional programmers
is to think about how they can use their
skills as a professional programmer not
just for business how can you change the
world in ways which aren't necessarily
directly correlate to making money
because are all the good things in the
world that we do directly correlated to
money I don't think they are and so
should programming be the same I don't
think it should I think we should be
thinking about how we can use our
amazing fabulous skills and we all have
that most people don't yet have to to
change the world for the good that we
see and part of that is building new
things also part of that is educate what
we know about programming the people who
don't know about it so that they
themselves could do the same things we
can do too I think that's a fantastic
closing statement thanks a lot Sam thank
you very much
getting software to your users quickly
and reliably is the most important part
of being a software engineer snap C is
cloud-based continuous integration and
continuous deployment tool lets you set
up in minutes with your github account
and within a few clicks we'll have your
first pipeline running discover and fix
your bugs quickly before pushing the
production by setting up stages from
simple ones to complex that run
automatically when you push your changes
need more speed
run tests in parallel with expanded
workers and get your feedback fast
deploy to Heroku AWS and more we even
integrate with slack to give you updates
on your builds go to snap dot CI slash
software radio and build test and deploy
free for 30 days
snap CI embodies the lessons that
thought Works has learned from 20 years
of software deployment the same lessons
that have been written about by Martin
Fowler and J's humble check it out at
snap CI slash software radio thanks for
listening to se Radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group online
plus our faces you can also email us at
team at SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SC radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]